Guide to the Alexander Boteler Papers, 1707-1924 RL.10102
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alexander Robinson Boteler papers
1707-1924
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Boteler, Henry, Dr.
Boteler, Alexander Robinson
RL.10102
3 Linear Feet 5 boxes, 1,686 items (incl. 4 vols.)
Correspondence of Alexander's father, Dr. Henry Boteler, for 1776-1837; and family letters of Alexander with information on his career at Princeton College and his courtship of his future wife, Helen Macomb Stockton. Political correspondence, relating to the election of 1860, the Constitutional Union party, and Alexander's travels around the country in 1882-1884 while a member of the U.S. tariff commission. Volumes include Boteler's diary for 1845, relative to his farming activities; various scrapbooks and some genealogical materials on the Pendleton, Digges, and Pope families. Among the correspondents are Lewis Cass, Samuel Cooper, John B. Floyd, S. B. French, Wade Hampton, T. J. Jackson, Andrew Johnson, R. E. Lee, John Letcher, W. P. Miles, John Page, Thomas N. Page, Rembrandt Peale, W. N. Pendleton, W. C. Rives, Alexander Robinson, W. H. Seward, J.E.B. Stuart, Jacob Thompson, J. F. Thompson, and Dabney C. Wirt.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical Note
Alexander R. Boteler (1815-1892) was Virginia political leader, congressman, and Civil War soldier. He graduated from Princeton College, Princeton, New Jersey. He was active in politics before the Civil War and much of his correspondence relates to the election of 1860 and the Constitutional Union Party. He was later a member of the U.S. Tariff Commission from 1882-1884.
Provenance
The Alexander Robinson Boteler papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library between 1935 and 1963.
Collection Overview
This collection consists of family letters of Alexander R. Boteler (1815-1892), Virginia political leader, congressman, and Civil War soldier, with sidelights on his career at Princeton College, Princeton, New Jersey, his courtship of Helen Macomb Stockton, whom he later married, his altercations with Charles J. Faulkner, and "Yankee" depredations at his home, "Fountain Rock," during the Civil War; political correspondence, 1855-1870, relating to the election of 1860 and the Constitutional Union Party; letters concerning Boteler's travels about the country in 1882-1884 while a member of the U.S. Tariff Commission; correspondence concerning claims of James Rumsey as inventor of the first steamboat; and legal and personal papers of Helen (Stockton) Boteler's father, Ebenezer S. Stockton, and grandfather, Robert Stockton. Volumes include Boteler's diary, 1845, relative to his farming activities; a scrapbook on the election of 1848; a scrapbook containing clippings, letters, and pictures devoted principally to the activities and interests of Boteler; and a scrapbook containing clippings, letters, and pictures concerning the Pendleton, Digges, and Pope families, especially the life of Dudley Digges Pendleton who married Helen Stockton Boteler.
The collection also contains the correspondence of Alexander R. Boteler's father, Dr. Henry Boteler, for 1776-1837. Among other correspondents are A. R. Boteler, Lewis Cass, Samuel Cooper, John B. Floyd, S. B. French, Wade Hampton, T. J. Jackson, Andrew Johnson, R. E. Lee, John Letcher, W. P. Miles, John Page, Thomas N. Page, Rembrandt Peale, W. N. Pendleton, W. C. Rives, Alexander Robinson, W. H. Seward, J. E. B. Stuart, Jacob Thompson, J. R. Thompson, Dabney C. Wirt.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Courtship -- West Virginia; West Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Farm life -- West Virginia; Stuart, Jeb; Pope family; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Boteler, Henry, Dr.; Cass, Lewis; Boteler, Alexander Robinson; Boteler, Helen Macomb Stockton; Princeton University; Pendleton family; Jackson, Stonewall; Johnson, Andrew; Digges family; Hampton, Wade; Constitutional Union Party (U.S.) -- Virginia; Cooper, Samuel
- Alexander Robinson Boteler papers, 1707-1924
  - Biographical/Genealogical materials, undated (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1707-1783 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1776-1855 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1856-1876 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1877-1885 Sept. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1885 Oct.-1910 and undated (Box 4)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 5)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 5)
  - Handwritten notes, undated (Box 5)
  - Biographical sketches, undated (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook I, 1771-1824 (Volume 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Scrapbook of clippings, letters and pictures which cover Boteler's family and his activities.
  - Scrapbook II, 1729-1887 (Volume F:376)
    Scrapbook concerns the genealogy of the Pendleton, Digges, and Pope familes, related by the marriage of Helen Stockton Boteler to Dudley Digges Pendleton.
  - Scrapbook, 1848 (Volume S:374)
    This scrapbook primarily concerns the presidential election of 1848.
  - Diary, 1845 (Volume S:373)
    Diary entries document Boteler's activities as a planter.